The brain's cleansing system has
only been recently discovered.
It may be a key component
to healthy cognition.
In this video and the next,
we look at how the
glymphatic system works and,
more importantly,
what we can do to
make it work even better.
"How Much Sleep Is Needed for
Glymphatic Flow (Brain Cleaning)?"
Sleep is a great mystery.
A trait shared
across animal species,
sleep must be
of vital importance
to survive
natural selection pressures
to eliminate
such a vulnerable state.
Indeed, cringeworthy experiments
have shown
that keeping animals awake
long enough
can be fatal within
eleven to thirty-two days.
It turns out
sleep is of-the-brain,
by the brain,
and for the brain.
One function of sleep that has
been elucidated in recent years
is the clearance
of toxic waste byproducts
through a newly discovered
drainage system in the brain.
With the invention
of the encephalogram, EEG,
to measure brain wave activity,
the scientific world
was quickly disabused
of the notion that sleep was
a time of rest for the brain.
During certain stages of sleep
there is brain-wide activity
going on,
but what was
the brain actively doing?
More than 2,000 years ago,
Aristotle proposed that sleep
helps the body clean the blood.
Today, we know sleep may help
the body clean the brain.
Until 2012, we thought
that the brain was singular
among organs for recycling
nearly all of its own waste.
It had to,
since it was separated
from the rest of the body
by the blood-brain barrier.
But the barrier that keeps
toxins out of the brain
presumably keeps toxins in.
Then, in 2012,
a brain-wide
fluid transport network
was discovered,
termed the glymphatic system.
By microscopically tracking dye
injected into the brains
of mice,
scientists discovered
fluid-filled tunnels
surrounding blood vessels
in the brain.
The pressure wave
of arterial pulses
with every heartbeat
milks the fluid along
before eventually draining
into the cerebrospinal fluid
surrounding the brain.
What does this
have to do with sleep?
The whole system is only
really active when sleeping.
During wakefulness,
these tunnels are clamped down,
reducing glymphatic flow
by 90 percent.
The thought is the fluid shifts
might interfere
with targeted neurotransmitter
chemical communication
in the awake state.
So the biological need for sleep
may reflect the need
for the brain to enter
into a state to filter out
potentially neurotoxic waste
products like beta amyloid,
which is implicated
in Alzheimer's disease.
Perhaps this could help explain
why those who routinely get
fewer than seven hours of sleep
a night are at increased risk
of developing cognitive
disorders such as dementia.
Randomizing individuals
to have their sleep disrupted
by a series of beeps
administered through headphones
in a sleep lab
increases amyloid levels,
whereas improving sleep,
by treating sleep apnea patients
with CPAP, for example,
improves slow wave activity,
deep sleep, and appears
to lower amyloid levels.
PET scans show
even a single all-nighter
can cause
a significant increase
in accumulation of beta amyloid
in critical brain areas.
The problem is that
glymphatic brain filtration
appears to decline with aging.
Old mice only have
10 to 20 percent
the glymphatic function
of young mice.
This could be due
to a number of factors.
As we age,
we experience less
of the deep, slow wave sleep,
the type of sleep during
which brain waste clearance
appears to be the most active.
Further contributing
to the stagnancy,
our arteries tend
to stiffen as we age,
reducing the pulsations
that drive the glymphatic pump.
That also offers
one potential explanation
as to why hypertension
is tied to dementia.
The thickening of artery walls
with high blood pressure
also has a stiffening effect.
How can we counter this
age-related glymphatic decline
and keep our brains cleaner?
We'll explore
just that question, next.